Samuel Ruben Papers, 1923-1979 RG.015
Poly Archives & Special Collections at Bern Dibner Library of Science and Technology
Guide to the Samuel Ruben Papers, 1923-1979
RG.015
Poly Archives & Special Collections at Bern Dibner Library of Science and Technology
2.0 Cubic feet 4 boxes
Samuel Ruben was born in 1900. He was an American inventor who made lasting contributions to the fields of electrochemistry and solid-state technology. While he dropped out of college and had no formal education, his scientific career spanned over 60 years. Ruben worked extensively with the Duracell Company and is credited with revolutionizing battery technology. In 1967, Ruben endowed a scholarship for Polytechnic students. In April 1979, he was inducted as a Fellow of Polytechnic Institute of New York. An exhibition of his inventions was displayed to mark the occasion.
Samuel Ruben, 1900-1988
Biographical/Historical note
Samuel Ruben was born on 14 July 1900 in Harrison, New Jersey. He was an American inventor who made lasting contributions to the fields of electrochemistry and solid-state technology. While he dropped out of college and had no formal education, his scientific career spanned over 60 years. Ruben produced over 300 patents, many of which were developed at Ruben Laboratories in New Rochelle, which he founded. Ruben held honorary degrees from Polytechnic Institute of New York (where he was also an honorary Professor), Butler University, and Columbia University.
In the 1920’s, Ruben’s dry electrolytic capacitors made possible the first low-cost plug-in radios with greater durability, significantly longer shelf life, and longer operating lifetime. Ruben’s improvement to the AC Vacuum Tube shortened the warm-up time and extended the lifetime of the product. This technology was used in the Boulder Dam generators, among others. The Photolytic Cell was capable of noise-free response to audio frequencies. The Ruben Vacuum Tube Relay responded to audio and radio frequencies and found application in various remote-controlled devices, such as railway signal systems, telephone relay circuits, and general call systems. Other inventions include the Glass Mesh Fluorescent Tube, a portable gamma detector, and a device that was commercially applied to phonographs which created an improved low frequency response.
The licensee of many of his inventions was P.R. Mallory Company, which later became Duracell. Ruben and Philip Rogers Mallory invented the mercury button cell in 1942 in response to an urgent need created during World War II for a miniature battery that would not deteriorate in tropical climates and would be capable of maintaining voltage on loads and retaining transmission range. The sealed alkaline cell made possible the miniature batteries used in implanted cardiac pacemakers, hearing aides, watches, cameras, transistor radios and other electronic devices. He died on 16 July 1988 in Oregon.
Sources: Fowler, Glenn (20 July 1988). "Samuel Ruben, 88, an Inventor Noted for Electrochemical Work". New York Times. Retrieved 2013-06-28.
Scope and Contents note
The collection includes patents (1928-1976) and materials relating to Ruben’s induction as a Fellow of the Polytechnic Institute of New York (1975-1979). Forty of Ruben’s inventions were displayed in an exhibition commemorating this event. Supporting materials provide information about each object and include documents, literature (1923-1978), correspondence (1975-1979), photographs, and realia. The collection also includes documents relating to the endowed scholarship Ruben left to Polytechnic in 1967. The scholarships were to be awarded to two undergraduate students per year studying chemical engineering. Finally, the collection contains a small number of articles written about Ruben and his work.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research without restrictions.
Related Archival Materials note
Samuel Rubens papers, Othmer Library of Chemical History, Chemical Heritage Foundation, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania.
Arrangement note
Series I contains 162 of Ruben's patents approved by the United State Patents and Trademark Office. Serices II contains documents relating to the exhibition held in honor of Ruben's induction as a Fellow of Polytechnic Institute of New York. Series III contains coorespondence and articles relating to the endowed scholarship gift by Ruben. Series IV contains articles written about Ruben and his work.
Bugliarello, George, (Georgio Bugliarello-Wondrich), 1927-2011; Cohan, Leonard; Polytechnic Institute of New York.; Smithsonian Institution.; Articles; Clippings; Correspondence; Dry-cell batteries; Electrochemistry; Exhibition records; Monographs; Patents; Photographs; Publications; Speeches
- Series I: Patents, 1928-1976
  Arrangement note
  The patents series consists of 162 of Ruben’s patents and are arranged by patent number.
  - Patent Number 3940284, Nickel Oxide Electric Current Producing Cell, 1976 February 24 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Patent Number 3870563, Hermetically Sealed Storage Battery, 1975 March 11 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Patent Number 3798070, Lead-Acid Storage Battery with Titanyl Sulfate Buffered Electrolyte, 1974 March 19 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Patent Number 3615831, Lead Oxide-Sulfuric Acid Battery Having a Positive Electrode Comprising a Titanium-Molybdenum-Zirconium Alloy Grid, 1971 October 26 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Patent Number 3576674, Lead Peroxide-Sulfuric Acid Cell, 1971 April 27 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Patent Number 3544375, Rechargeable Fuel Cell, 1970 December 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Patent Number 3539398, Magnesium Primary Cell, 1970 November 10 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Patent Number 3499795, Storage Battery Having Electrodes Comprising a Supporting Base of Titanium Nitride, 1970 March 10 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Patent Number 3455738, Method of Making Rechargeable Cell Having Ionically Permeable Gel and Electrode Therefor, 1969 July 15 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Patent Number 3486940, Storage Battery Having a Positive Electrode Comprising a Supporting Base of Titanium Nitride Having a Surface Film of Non-Polarizing Material, 1969 December 13 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Patent Number 3485672, Electric Current Producing Cell, 1969 December 23 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Patent Number 3485675, Electric Current Producing Cell Having Depolarizer in Intimate Contact with Carburized Surface of the Container, 1969 December 23 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Patent Number 3486063, Incandescent Lamp, 1969 December 23 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Patent Number 3352769, Process for Producing Microperforated Stainless Steel Sheets, 1967 November 14 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Patent Number 3275572, Refractory Composition and Electrical Resistance Made Therefrom, 1966 September 27 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Patent Number 3216955, Electrical Resistor, 1965 November 9 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Patent Number 3161545, Rechargeable Cell and Electrode Therefor, 1964 December 15 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Patent Number 3152293, Sealed Semiconductor Device and Mounting Means Therefor, 1964 October 6 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Patent Number 3124728, Sealed Electrolytic Capacitor, 1964 March 10 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Patent Number 3088991, Electric Current Producing Cell, 1963 May 17 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Patent Number 3066179, Electric Current Producing Cell, 1962 November 27 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Patent Number 3048645, Primary Dry Cell, 1962 August 17 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Patent Number 3006865, Refractory Composition, 1961 October 31 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Patent Number 2967898, Primary Cell, 1961 January 10 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Patent Number 2954418, Lead Peroxide Dry Cell, 1960 September 27 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Patent Number 2948769, Electric Current Producing Cell, 1960 August 9 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Patent Number 2948768, Sulfamate Primary Cell, 1960 August 9 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Patent Number 24830 Reissue 2810006, Electric Current Producing Cell, 1960 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Patent Number 2862156, Dry Capacitor, 1958 November 25 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Patent Number 2852591, Potential Producing Cell and Battery Pile, 1958 September 16 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Patent Number 2816151, Potential Producing Cell, 1957 December 10 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Patent Number 2814664, Electric Current Producing Cell, 1957 November 26 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Patent Number 2810006, Electric Current Producing Cell, 1957 October 15 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Patent Number 2798112, Reserve Type Dry Cell, 1957 July 2 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Patent Number 2783292, Primary Cell, 1957 February 26 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Patent Number 2711497, Alternating Current Rectifier and Method of Making the Same, 1957 June 21 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Patent Number 2711496, Lead Peroxide Rectifiers and Method of Making the Same, 1955 June 21 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Patent Number 2708242, Radiation Dosimeter, 1955 May 10 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Patent Number 2707199 Potential Producing Cell and High Voltage Pile, 1955 April 26 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Patent Number 2692215, Alkaline Dry Cell, 1954 October 19 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Patent Number 2669597, Electric Current Producing Cell with Tin Anode, 1954 February 16 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Patent Number 2638489, Primary Cell, 1953 May 12 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Patent Number 2631181, Alkaline Dry Cell, 1953 March 10 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Patent Number 2629758, Electric Current Producing Cell and Electrolyte Therefor, 1953 February 24 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Patent Number 2621368, Alkaline Dry Cell, 1952 December 2 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Patent Number 2606941, Primary Cell and Battery, 1952 August 12 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Patent Number 2576266, Electrolyte for Alkaline Dry Cells, 1951 November 27 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Patent Number 2571616, Electric Current Producing Cells, 1951 October 16 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Patent Number 2562215, Primary Cells, 1951 July 31 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Patent Number 2554504, Rechargeable Cell, 1951 May 29 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Patent Number 2542710, Alkaline Dry Cell, 1951 February 20 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Patent Number 2542576, Alkaline Cylindrical Dry Cells, 1951 February 20 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Patent Number 2536699, Alkaline Dry Cells, 1951 January 2 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Patent Number 2536698, Battery Cell and Unit, 1951 January 2 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Patent Number 2536697, Primary Cell and Battery, 1951 January 2 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Patent Number 2536696, Primary Cell, 1951 January 2 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Patent Number 2527576, Flat Primary Cell, 1950 October 31 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Patent Number 2499419, Alkaline Primary Cell with Permanganate Depolarizer, 1950 March 17 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Patent Number 2482514, Primary Cell with Mercury Absorbents, 1949 September 20 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Patent Number 2481539, Method of Making Depolarizer Units for Alkaline Primary Cells, 1949 September 13 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Patent Number 2473546, Alkaline Primary Cell, 1949 June 21 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Patent Number 2463565, Dry Primary Cell, 1949 March 8 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Patent Number 2463316, Alkaline Dry Cells with Permanganate Cathodes, 1949 March 1 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Patent Number 2424904, Process for the Treatment of Regenerated Sheet Cellulose to Improve its Dielectric Properties, 1947 July 29 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Patent Number 2422046, Alkaline Dry Cell, 1947 June 10 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Patent Number 2422045, Alkaline Dry Cell, 1947 June 10 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Patent Number 2393068, Electrodeposition of Insulating Materials, 1946 January 15 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Patent Number 2389640, High Frequency Ignition System, 1945 November 27 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Patent Number 2389638, Ignition System, 1945 November 27 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Patent Number 2387772, Electrodeposition, Methods and Apparatus, 1945 October 13 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Patent Number 2378160, Dielectric, 1945 June 12 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Patent Number 2375178, Variable Electrical Resistors, 1945 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Patent Number 2360367, Electrostatic Condensers and Dielectrics Therefor, 1944 October 17 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Patent Number 2355680, Electrical Resistor Device, 1944 August 15 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Patent Number 2348311, Electrode Elements for Dry Disk Rectifiers, 1944 May 9 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Patent Number 2313093, Dielectric for Electrostatic Condensers, 1943 March 9 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Patent Number 2308545, Dielectrics for Electrostatic Condensers and Condensers Made Therefrom, 1943 January 19 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Patent Number 2327462, Electrodeposition of Insulating Material, 1943 August 24 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Patent Number 2307005, Methods of Treating Metal Compositions, 1942 December 29 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Patent Number 2306409, Primary Cell, 1942 December 29 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Patent Number 2306408, Magnesium Primary Cell, 1942 December 29 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Patent Number 2287834, Gas Discharge Devices and Circuit Therefor, 1942 June 13 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Patent Number 2276346, Dielectric Composition, 1942 March 17 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Patent Number 2282344, Resistance Devices, 1942 May 12 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Patent Number 2266814, Dielectric Compositions, 1941 December 23 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Patent Number 2266813, Dielectrics for Electrostatic Condensers, 1941 December 23 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Patent Number 2266812, Electric Condensers and Dielectrics Therefor, 1941 December 23 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Patent Number 2266811, Dielectrics for Electrostatic Condensers and the Like, 1941 December 23 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Patent Number 2266810, Dielectrics for Electrostatic Condensers, 1941 December 23 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Patent Number 2266809, Electrostatic Condensers and Dielectrics Therefor, 1941 December 23 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Patent Number 2257129, Magnesium Primary Cell, 1941 September 13 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Patent Number 2255817, Electrolytes for Electrolytic Condensers, 1941 September 16 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - Patent Number 2255818, Gas Discharge Device, 1941 September 16 (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - Patent Number 2253533, Electric Make and Break Contact, 1941 August 26 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Patent Number 2235566, Electrostatic Condensers, 1941 March 18 (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Patent Number 2213969, Electrical Resistance Element, 1940 September 10 (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - Patent Number 2211584, Coaxial Electrical Conductors, 1940 August 13 (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - Patent Number 2211583, Methods of Making Electric Condensers and Condensers Made Thereby, 1940 August 13 (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - Patent Number 2211582, Process of Electrolytically Coating Nonconductive Materials, 1940 August 13 (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - Patent Number 2204623, Variable Resistors, 1940 June 18 (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - Patent Number 2200301, Potential-Producing Cells, 1940 May 14 (Box 1, Folder 101)
  - Patent Number 2199446, Electrolytic Condensers, 1940 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 102)
  - Patent Number 2199445, Electrolytic Condensers and Methods of Preparing Etched Electrodes Therefor, 1940 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 103)
  - Patent Number 2198843, Methods of Making a Rectifier Element, 1940 April 13 (Box 1, Folder 104)
  - Patent Number 2178970, Electrolytic Condenser, 1939 November 7 (Box 1, Folder 105)
  - Patent Number 2178969, Potential Producing Cell, 1939 November 7 (Box 1, Folder 106)
  - Patent Number 2170066, Fluorescent Lamps, 1939 August 22 (Box 1, Folder 107)
  - Patent Number 2166180, Electrolytic Condenser, 1939 July 18 (Box 1, Folder 108)
  - Patent Number 2166179, Film Maintaining Electrolytes, 1939 July 18 (Box 1, Folder 109)
  - Patent Number 2127756, Electric Lamp, 1938 August 23 (Box 1, Folder 110)
  - Patent Number 2116215, Electrical Switch, 1938 May 3 (Box 1, Folder 111)
  - Patent Number 2115399, Photovoltaic Cell, 1938 April 26 (Box 1, Folder 112)
  - Patent Number 2104817, Photoelectric Relay, 1938 January 11 (Box 1, Folder 113)
  - Patent Number 2066912, Electrolytic Condensers, 1937 January 5 (Box 1, Folder 114)
  - Patent Number 2063524, Electrical Amplifier Circuit, 1936 December 8 (Box 1, Folder 115)
  - Patent Number 2063340, Continuous Torque Impulse Motor, 1936 December 8 (Box 1, Folder 116)
  - Patent Number 2050587, Electrolytic Condenser, 1936 August 11 (Box 1, Folder 117)
  - Patent Number 2049139, Electrical Discharge Relay, 1936 July 28 (Box 1, Folder 118)
  - Patent Number 2032439, Electric Current Rectifier, 1936 March 3 (Box 1, Folder 119)
  - Patent Number 2014239, Rectifier Device, 1935 September 10 (Box 1, Folder 120)
  - Patent Number 2001978, Voltaic Couple, 1935 May 21 (Box 1, Folder 121)
  - Patent Number 1991175, Oscillator Circuits, 1935 February 12 (Box 1, Folder 122)
  - Patent Number 1989461, Ionic Amplifier, 1935 January 29 (Box 1, Folder 123)
  - Patent Number 1989464, Electric Current Rectifier, 1935 January 29 (Box 1, Folder 124)
  - Patent Number 1989463, Electric Current Rectifier, 1935 January 29 (Box 1, Folder 125)
  - Patent Number 1989462, Ionic Amplifier, 1935 January 29 (Box 1, Folder 126)
  - Patent Number 1985519, Vacuum Tube Circuit, 1934 December 25 (Box 1, Folder 127)
  - Patent Number 1971053, Resistance Device, 1934 August 21 (Box 1, Folder 128)
  - Patent Number 1941494, Reissue 19218, Light-Sensitive Device, 1934 June 19 (Box 1, Folder 129)
  - Patent Number 1941493, Light Sensitive Circuit, 1934 January 2 (Box 1, Folder 130)
  - Patent Number 1920151, Potential Producing Cell, 1933 July 25 (Box 1, Folder 131)
  - Patent Number 1918716, Electrical Condenser, 1933 July 18 (Box 1, Folder 132)
  - Patent Number 1916235, Remote Control Device, 1933 July 4 (Box 1, Folder 133)
  - Patent Number 1902900, Electrical Phonograph Pick-Up, 1933 March 28 (Box 1, Folder 134)
  - Patent Number 1896043, Insulated Wires and Processes Therefor, 1933 January 31 (Box 1, Folder 135)
  - Patent Number 1896042, Insulated Wire, 1933 January 31 (Box 1, Folder 136)
  - Patent Number 1896041, Insulated Wire, 1933 January 31 (Box 1, Folder 137)
  - Patent Number 1896040, Insulated Wire and Process Therefor, 1933 January 31 (Box 1, Folder 138)
  - Patent Number 1895489, Methods and an Apparatus for Electrically Effecting Synthetic Reactions, 1933 January 31 (Box 1, Folder 139)
  - Patent Number 1890470, Electric Current Rectifier, 1932 December 13 (Box 1, Folder 140)
  - Patent Number 1889380, Device and Method for Recording Sound Wave, 1932 November 29 (Box 1, Folder 141)
  - Patent Number 1889379, Methods of Making an Electrical Resistance Element, 1932 November 29 (Box 1, Folder 142)
  - Patent Number 1882449, Electron Discharge Device, 1932 October 11 (Box 1, Folder 143)
  - Patent Number 1877482, Resistance Device, 1932 September 13 (Box 1, Folder 144)
  - Patent Number 1849157, Insulating Coating for Filament, 1932 March 15 (Box 1, Folder 145)
  - Patent Number 1847669, Electron Tube Apparatus, 1932 March 1 (Box 1, Folder 146)
  - Patent Number 1843698, Apparatus for Generating Electrical Potential, 1932 February 2 (Box 1, Folder 147)
  - Patent Number 1829237, Heater Element and Methods for Making it, 1931 October 27 (Box 1, Folder 148)
  - Patent Number 1815483, Reissue 18713, Electrical Discharge Device, 1933 January 17 (Box 1, Folder 149)
  - Patent Number 1805108, Electric Discharge Display Device, 1931 May 12 (Box 1, Folder 150)
  - Patent Number 1799646, Sound-Emitting Apparatus, 1931 April 7 (Box 1, Folder 151)
  - Patent Number 1781033, Electrical Condensers, 1930 November 11 (Box 1, Folder 152)
  - Patent Number 1757547, Phonograph Pick-Ups, 1930 May 6 (Box 1, Folder 153)
  - Patent Number 1755796, Electron-Tube Apparatus, 1930 April 22 (Box 1, Folder 154)
  - Patent Number 1752811, Methods and Apparatus of Telephonic Communication, 1930 April 1 (Box 1, Folder 155)
  - Patent Number 1751888, Sound-Emitting Device, 1930 March 25 (Box 1, Folder 156)
  - Patent Number 1748620, Microphone, 1930 February 25 (Box 1, Folder 157)
  - Patent Number 1747648, Ionic-Discharge Device, 1930 Februray 18 (Box 1, Folder 158)
  - Patent Number 1714191, Electrical Condenser, 1929 May 21 (Box 1, Folder 159)
  - Patent Number 1710073, Electrical Condenser, 1929 April 23 (Box 1, Folder 160)
  - Patent Number 1705538, Vacuum Tube, 1929 March 19 (Box 1, Folder 161)
  - Patent Number 1694190, Photo-Electric Cell, 1928 December 4 (Box 1, Folder 162)
- Series II: Exhibition, 1975-1979; A zinc mercuric dioxysulfate/zinc Sulfate cell, a non alkaline dry cell, was pasted onto number 40 of an inventory list (box 2, folder 3).
  Biographical/Historical note
  On April 24, 1979, Ruben was inducted as a Fellow of Polytechnic Institute of New York to celebrate 50 years of his pioneering electrochemistry and electronic achievements. Forty of Ruben's inventions were displayed at 333 Jay Street at the Brooklyn campus in an exhibition marking the occasion. Leonard Cohan, Director of the Polytechnic Libraries, worked with Ruben to curate the exhibition. Correspondence relating to the exhibition includes a draft of Cohan's speech for Ruben's fellow induction ceremony. Ruben sent Cohan literature, notes, and summaries which provided important contextual and background information for each object. The photographs and most of the literature and patents were numbered according to the related exhibition number. A similar exhibition was displayed around 1970 at the Smithsonian Institute, Washington, D.C. Photographs of the displays and objects are included. Realia is also included in the collection which consist of a plaque commemorating Ruben's laboratory, a battery, and a set of keys.
  - Subseries A: Supporting Documents, 1975-1979
    - Correspondence, 1975-1979 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Invoices, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Inventory Lists, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Subseries B: Supporting Literature, 1923-1978
    Three bound volumes and the oversize micellaneous literature folder are located in oversize box number 4.
    - Published Articles, 1923-1949 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Published Articles, 1966-1975, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - "A Description of Samuel Ruben's Historical Equipment," undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Published Articles Numbered According to Related Exhibition Object Number, 1945-1971, undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Oversized Miscellaneous Literature, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - "The Evolution of Electric Batteries in Response to Industrial Needs." Philadelphia: Dorrance & Company, 1978., Bound volume. (Box 4, Object 1)
    - "The Founders of Electrochemistry." Philadelphia: Dorrance & Company, 1975. (Box 4, Object 2)
    - "The Handbook of the Elements." Indianapolis: H. W. Sams, 1967. (Box 4, Object 3)
  - Subseries C: Photographs, circa 1970-1979
    - Photograph Numbers 1 - 5c, 1979? (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Photograph Numbers 6 - 10c, 1979? (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Photograph Numbers 11 - 22, 1979? (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Photograph Numbers 23 - 41, 1979? (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Smithsonian Institution Photographs, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Miscellaneous Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Subseries D: Realia
    - Plaque, 1979 (Box 4, Object 4)
    - Battery, undated (Box 4, Object 5)
    - Keys, undated (Box 4, Object 6)
- Series III: The Ruben Scholarships, 1967-1968
  - The Ruben Scholarships, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- Series IV: Articles, 1967-1968 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Articles, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 12)